<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!--<?rfc strict="no"?> -->

<rfc category="bcp"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-ietf-netmod-artwork-folding-latest">
    <front>
      <title abbrev="Handling Long Lines in Inclusions">Handling Long Lines in Inclusions in Internet-Drafts and RFCs</title>
        <author initials="K." surname="Watsen" fullname="Kent Watsen">
            <organization>Watsen Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>kent+ietf@watsen.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="Q." surname="Wu" fullname="Qin Wu">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <email>bill.wu@huawei.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Farrel" fullname="Adrian Farrel" >
            <organization>Old Dog Consulting</organization>
            <address>
                <email>adrian@olddog.co.uk</email>
            </address>
       </author>
       <author initials="B." surname="Claise" fullname="Benoît Claise" >
           <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems, Inc.">Cisco Systems,
           Inc.</organization>
           <address>
             <email>bclaise@cisco.com</email>
           </address>
        </author>

        <date/>
        <area>Operations</area>
        <workgroup>NETMOD Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>sourcecode</keyword>
        <keyword>artwork</keyword>
        <abstract>
          <t>This document introduces a simple and yet time-proven strategy for
          handling long lines in inclusions in drafts using a backslash ('\')
          character where line-folding has occurred.  The strategy works on any
          text-based content, but is primarily intended for a structured
          sequence of lines, such as would be referenced by the &lt;sourcecode&gt;
          element defined in Section 2.48 of RFC 7991, rather than for two-dimensional
          imagery, such as would be referenced by the &lt;artwork&gt; element
          defined in Section 2.5 of RFC 7991.  The approach produces consistent
          results, regardless of the content, that is both self-documenting and
          enables automated reconstitution of the original content.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
      <section title="Introduction">
        <t><xref target="RFC7994"/> sets out the requirements for
        plain-text RFCs and states that each line of an RFC (and hence of
        an Internet-Draft) must be limited to 72 characters followed by
        the character sequence that denotes an end-of-line (EOL).</t>

        <t>Internet-Drafts and RFCs often include example text or code
        fragments.  In order to render the formatting of such text it is
        usually presented as a figure using the "&lt;sourcecode&gt;"
        element in the source XML.  Many times the example text or code
        exceeds the 72 character line-length limit and the `xml2rfc`
        utility does not attempt to wrap the content of such inclusions,
        simply issuing a warning whenever lines exceed 69 characters.
        According to the RFC Editor, there is currently no convention
        in place for how to handle long lines, other than advising
        authors to clearly indicate what manipulation has occurred.</t>

        <t>This document introduces a simple and yet time-proven strategy for
        handling long lines in inclusions in drafts using a backslash ('\')
        character where line-folding has occurred.  The strategy works on any
        text based inclusion, but is primarily intended for a structured
        sequence of lines, such as would be referenced by the &lt;sourcecode&gt;
        element defined in Section 2.48 of <xref target="RFC7991"/>, rather
        than for two-dimensional imagery, such as would be referenced by the
        &lt;artwork&gt; element defined in Section 2.5 of <xref target="RFC7991"/>.
        The approach produces consistent results, regardless of the content,
        that is both self-documenting and enables automated reconstitution
        of the original content.</t>

        <t>Note that text files are represent as lines having their first
        character in column 1, and a line length of N where the last
        character is in the Nth column and is immediately followed by an end
        of line character sequence.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability Statement">
        <t>The format and algorithm defined in this document may be used
          in any context, whether for IETF documents or in other situations
          where structured folding is desired.</t>
        <t>Within the IETF, this work is primarily targeted to xml2rfc v3
          &lt;sourcecode&gt; element (Section 2.48 of <xref target="RFC7991"/>)
          and xml2rfc v2 &lt;artwork&gt; element (Section 2.5 of
          <xref target="RFC7749"/>) that, for lack of a better option, is
          currently used for both source code and artwork.  This work may
          be also be used for the xml2rfc v3 &lt;artwork&gt; element
          (Section 2.5 of <xref target="RFC7991"/>) but, as described in
          <xref target="not-for-art"/>, it is generally not recommended.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language" anchor="requirements-language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
        "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
        when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Goals">
        <section title="Automated Folding of Long Lines in Text Content">
          <t>Automated folding of long lines is needed in order to support
          draft compilations that entail a) validation of source input
          files (e.g., XML, JSON, ABNF, ASN.1) and/or b) dynamic
          generation of output, using a tool that doesn't observe line
          lengths, that is stitched into the final document to be submitted.</t>
          <t>Generally, in order for tooling to be able to process input
          files, the files must be in their original/natural state, which
          may include having some long lines.  Thus, these source files
          need to be modified before inclusion in the document in order to
          satisfy the line length limits.  This modification SHOULD be
          automated to reduce effort and errors resulting from manual
          effort.</t>
          <t>Similarly, dynamically generated output (e.g., tree diagrams)
          must also be modified, if necessary, in order for the resulting
          document to satisfy the line length limits.  When needed, this effort
          again SHOULD be automated to reduce effort and errors
          resulting from manual effort.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Automated Reconstitution of the Original Text Content">
          <t>Automated reconstitution of the original content is needed to
          support validation of artwork extracted from documents.  YANG
          <xref target="RFC7950"/> modules are already extracted from
          Internet-Drafts and validated as part of the draft-submission
          process.  Additionally, there has been some discussion regarding
          needing to do the same for instance examples (i.e., XML/JSON
          documents) contained within Internet-Drafts (<xref target="yang-doctors-thread"/>).
          Thus, it SHOULD be possible to mechanically reconstitute the
          original text content in order to satisfy tooling input parsers.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Limitations">
        <section title="Not Recommended for Graphical Artwork" anchor="not-for-art">
          <t>While the solution presented in this document will work on any
          kind of text-based content, it is most useful on content that
          represents sourcecode (XML, JSON, etc.) or, more generally, on
          content that has not been laid out in two dimensions (e.g., diagrams).</t>
          <t>Fundamentally, the issue is whether the text content remains readable
          once folded.  Text content that is unpredictable is especially susceptible
          to looking bad when folded; falling into this category are most
          UML diagrams, YANG tree diagrams, and ASCII art in general.</t>
          <t>It is NOT RECOMMENDED to use the solution presented in
          this document on graphical artwork.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Doesn't Work as Well as Format-Specific Options">
          <t>The solution presented in this document works generically
          for all text-based content, as it only views content as plain
          text.  However, various formats sometimes have built-in mechanisms
          that are better suited to prevent long lines.</t>
          <t>For instance, both the `pyang` and `yanglint` utilities
          have the command line option "--tree-line-length" that can
          be used to indicate a desired maximum line length for when
          generating tree diagrams <xref target="RFC8340"/>.</t>
          <t>In another example, some source formats (e.g., YANG
          <xref target="RFC7950"/>) allow any quoted string to be
          broken up into substrings separated by a concatenation
          character (e.g., '+'), any of which can be on a different
          line.</t>
          <t>In yet another example, some languages allow factoring
          blocks of code into call outs, such as functions.  Using
          such call outs is especially helpful when in some deeply-nested
          code, as they typically reset the indentation back to the first
          column.</t>
          <t>It is RECOMMENDED that authors do as much as possible
          within the selected format to avoid long lines.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Folded Structure" anchor="folded-structure">
        <t>Text content that has been folded as specified by this document
         MUST contain the following structure.</t>
        <section title="Header" anchor="header">
          <t>The header is two lines long.</t>
          <t>The first line is the following 46-character string that
          MAY be surrounded by any number of printable characters.
          This first line cannot itself be folded.
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
NOTE: '\\' line wrapping per BCP XX (RFC XXXX)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>[Note to RFC Editor: Please replace XX and XXXX with the numbers
          assigned to this document and delete this note.  Please make this
          change in multiple places in this document.]</t>
          <t>The second line is a blank line.  This line provides visual
          separation for  readability.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Body">
          <t>The character encoding is the same as described in Section 2
          of <xref target="RFC7994"/>, except that, per <xref target="RFC7991"/>,
          tab characters are prohibited.</t>
          <t>Lines that have a backslash ('\') occurring as the last character in
          a line immediately followed by the end of line character sequence, when
          the subsequent line starts with a backslash ('\') as the first non-space
          (' ') character, are considered "folded".</t>
          <t>Really long lines may be folded multiple times.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Algorithm" anchor="algorithm">
        <t>This section describes the processes for folding and unfolding long
          lines when they are encountered in a single instance of text content.
          It is assumed that another process inserts/extracts the individual
          text content instances to/from an Internet-Draft or RFC.  For example,
          the `xiax` utility <xref target="xiax"/> does just this.</t>
        <section title="Automated Folding">
          <t>Determine the desired maximum line length from input to the
          automated line-wrapping process, such as from a command line
          parameter.  If no value is explicitly specified, the value "69"
          SHOULD be used.</t>
          <t>Ensure that the desired maximum line length is not less than
          the minimum header, which is 46 characters.  If the desired
          maximum line length is less than this minimum, exit (this text-based
          content cannot be folded).</t>
          <t>Scan the text content for horizontal tab characters.  If any
          horizontal tab characters appear, either resolve them to space
          characters or exit, forcing the input provider to convert them
          to space characters themselves first.</t>
          <t>Scan the text content to see if any line exceeds the desired maximum.
          If no line exceeds the desired maximum, exit (this text content does not
          need to be folded).</t>
          <t>Scan the text content to ensure no existing lines already end with a
          backslash ('\') character when the subsequent line starts with a
          backslash ('\') character as the first non-space (' ') character,
          as this would lead to an ambiguous result.  If such a line is found,
          exit (this text content cannot be folded).</t>
          <t>If this text content needs to and can be folded, insert the header as
          described in <xref target="header" />.</t>
          <t>For each line in the text content, from top-to-bottom, if the line exceeds
          the desired maximum, then fold the line at the desired maximum column
          by 1) inserting the character backslash ('\') character at the maximum
          column, 2) inserting the end of line character sequence, inserting any
          number of space (' ') characters, and 4) inserting a further backslash
          ('\') character.</t>
          <t>The result of this previous operation is that the next line starts
          with an arbitrary number of space (' ') characters, followed by a
          backslash ('\') character, immediately followed by the character that
          was previously in the maximum column.</t>
          <t>Continue in this manner until reaching the end of the text content.  Note
          that this algorithm naturally addresses the case where the remainder
          of a folded line is still longer than the desired maximum, and hence
          needs to be folded again, ad infinitum.</t>
          <t>The process described in this section is illustrated by the "fold_it()"
          function in <xref target="script" />.</t>
          <section title="Manual Folding">
            <t>Authors may choose to fold text examples and source code by
            hand to produce a text content that is more pleasant for a human reader
            but which can still be automatically unfolded (as described in
            <xref target="unfold-alg"/>) to produce single lines that are
            longer than the maximum document line length.</t>
            <t>For example, an author may choose to make the fold at convenient
            gaps between words such that the backslash is placed in a lower
            column number than the text content's maximum column value.</t>
            <t>Additionally, an author may choose to indent the start of a
            continuation line by inserting space characters before the line
            continuation marker backslash character.</t>
            <t>Manual folding may also help handle the cases that cannot be
            automatically folded as described in <xref target="algorithm" />.</t>
            <t>Authors MUST produce a result that adheres to the structure
            described in <xref target="folded-structure"/>.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Automated Unfolding" anchor="unfold-alg">
          <t>All unfolding is assumed to be automated although a reader will
          mentally perform the act of unfolding the text to understand the true
          nature of the original text content.</t>
          <t>Scan the beginning of the text content for the header described in
          <xref target="header"/>.  If the header is not present, starting
          on the first line of the text content, exit (this artwork does not
          need to be unfolded).</t>
          <t>Remove the 2-line header from the text content.</t>
          <t>For each line in the text content, from top-to-bottom, if the line has
          a backslash ('\') character immediately followed by the end of line
          character sequence, and if the next line has a backslash ('\') character
          as the first non-space (' ') character, then the lines can be unfolded.
          Remove the first backslash ('\') character, the end of line character
          sequence, any leading space (' ') characters, and the second backslash
          ('\') character, which will bring up the next line.  Then continue to
          scan each line in the text content starting with the current line (in case
          it was multiply folded).</t>
          <t>Continue in this manner until reaching the end of the text content.</t>
          <t>The process described in this section is illustrated by the "unfold_it()"
          function in <xref target="script" />.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="example" title="Examples">
        <t>The following self-documenting examples illustrate folded
        text-based content.</t>

        <t>The source text content cannot be presented here, as it would again need
        to be folded. Alas, only the result can be provided.</t>

        <t>The examples in Sections 8.1 through 8.4 were automatically folded
        on column 69, the default value.  Section 8.5 shows an example of
        manual folding.</t>

        <section title="Simple Example Showing Boundary Conditions">
          <t>This example illustrates a boundary condition test using
          numbers for counting purposes.  The input contains 5 lines,
          each line one character longer than the previous.</t>

          <t>Any printable character (including ' ' and '\') can be used
          as a substitute for any number, except for on the 4th row,
          the trailing '9' is not allowed to be a '\' character if the
          first non-space character of the next line is a '\' character,
          as that would lead to an ambiguous result.</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/example-1.txt.folded)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Example Showing Multiple Wraps of a Single Line">

        <t>This example illustrates one very long line (280 characters).</t>

        <t>Any printable character (including ' ' and '\') can be used
        as a substitute for any number.</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/example-2.txt.folded)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Example With Native Backslash">
        <t>This example has a '\' character in the wrapping column.  The native text
           includes the sequence "fish\fowl" with the '\' character occurring on the
           69th column.</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/example-3.txt.folded)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Example With Native Whitespace">
        <t>This example has whitespace spanning the wrapping column.  The native input
        contains 15 space (' ') characters between "like" and "white".</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/example-4.txt.folded)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Example of Manual Wrapping">
        <t>This example was manually wrapped to cause the folding to occur
        after each term, putting each term on its own line.  Indentation
        is used to additionally improve readability.  Also note that the
        mandatory header is surrounded by different printable characters
        than shown in the other examples.</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/example-5.txt.prefolded)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>The manual folding produces a more readable result than the following
        equivalent folding that contains no indentation.</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/example-5.txt.prefolded.unfolded)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-cons">
        <t>This BCP has no Security Considerations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-cons">
        <t>This BCP has no IANA Considerations.</t>
      </section>

    </middle>

    <back>

      <references title="Normative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
      </references>

      <references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7950.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7749.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7991.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7994.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8340.xml"?>
        <reference anchor="yang-doctors-thread" target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/msg/yang-doctors/DCfBqgfZPAD7afzeDFlQ1Xm2X3g">
          <front>
            <title>[yang-doctors] automating yang doctor reviews</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="xiax" target="https://pypi.org/project/xiax/">
          <front><title>The `xiax` Python Package</title><author/><date/></front>
        </reference>
      </references>


      <!-- APPENDICIES -->
      <section title="POSIX Shell Script" anchor="script">
        <t>This non-normative appendix section includes a shell script
          that can both fold and unfold text content.  Note that this
          script is applied only to single text content instances.</t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(fold-artwork.sh)
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
        <t>The authors thank the following folks for their various
        contributions (sorted by first name):
        Gianmarco Bruno, Italo Busi, Jonathan Hansford, Joel Jaeggli,
        Lou Berger, Martin Bjorklund, Italo Busi, and Rob Wilton.</t>
        <t>The authors additionally thank the RFC Editor for confirming
        that there is no set convention today for handling long lines in
        artwork/sourcecode inclusions. </t>
      </section>
    </back>

</rfc>
